Finding Aid for Sunrise Cooperative Farm Community Records, 1933-1937
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sunrise Cooperative Farm Community records 1933-1937
Sunrise Cooperative Farm Community.
85446 Bj 2 BJ Outsize
Jewish settlement established during the depression in Alicia near Saginaw; include minutes and reports, newsletters, financial records, membership materials, and court papers.
2 linear feet
2 microfilms
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of this record group came from Philip Trupin (donor no. 6638 ) in 1981. A letter containing remembrances came from Samuel Gonick (donor no. 3976 ) in 1962.
The record group is open to research.
The Sunrise Cooperative Farm Community was founded in 1933 by New York anarchist Joseph Cohen. Located on an established, economically depressed farm near Alicia in Saginaw County, the commune was intended as a Jewish self-help agrarian colony in which everyone would work for the good of all and disparities of wealth would not exist. The membership requirements were strict and meant to insure the success of this experiment in cooperative farming. No one over age 45 were permitted to join. There would be no large families with many children, nor would conservatives, religious people, or professed communists be allowed to join. Although most members were Jewish, this was not a requirement.
The Community drew members from fourteen states. Each was required to pay a membership fee, some of which went to pay hired men needed to restore the neglected farm to commercial viability. Financial stability would always be a problem for the commune as would organizational struggles within the commune.
By 1936, many of the original members hoped to return to the cities for steadier employment opportunities. Others looked to the government's Resettlement Administration to purchase the farm and then resell it in smaller parcels with assistance given to the building of homes, barns, and fences. The sale was finalized on December 7, 1936. With the sale, a large portion of the settlers moved away. Others, who hoped to continue the communal existence, took their share of the sale and purchased a farm in Samos, Middlesex County, Virginia.
The Sunrise Cooperative Farm Community records document the organization and operation of the farming community. The record group is divided into the following series: Historical/Informational; Minutes and other organizational records; Newsletters; Financial Records; Membership Materials; Topical Files; and Litigation.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan--Saginaw County.; Alicia (Mich.); Cooperative societies--Michigan--Saginaw County.; Depressions--1929--Michigan--Saginaw County.; Jews--Michigan.; Saginaw (Mich.); Sunrise Cooperative Farm Community.
Contributors:
Abbott, Leonard Dalton, 1878-1953.; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955.; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940.; Hall, Bolton, 1854-1938.; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968.
- Historical/Informational
  - Retrospective articles about the cooperative 1982-1997 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Historical and informational material (Box 1)
- Minutes and other organizational records
  - Constitution and by laws (Box 1)
  - Minutes and reports 1933 (Box 1)
    - August-September 1933 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1933 (Box 1)
  - Executive Board minutes 1934-1937 (Box 1)
    - 1934-1935, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1935-1937, 1 oversize volumes (Volume 1)
  - Organization and regulations 1933 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and other miscellaneous papers (indexed correspondence) (Box 1)
    (include telegram from Emma Goldman)
- Newsletters
  - Newsletter: Sunrise News
    - April-May 1934 (Box 1)
    - June-July 1934 (Box 1)
    - August-September 1934 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1934 (Box 1)
    - January-April 1935 (Box 1)
    - May-July 1935 (Box 1)
    - August-December 1935 (Box 1)
  - Newsletter: Out at Sunrise, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters (Sunrise schools) (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Sunrise schools) (Box 1)
- Financial records
  - Weekly cash statements January-June 1936 (Box 1)
  - Weekly cash statements July 1936-January 1937 (Box 1)
  - Audit and financial reports 1933 (Box 1)
  - Audit and financial reports 1934 (Box 1)
  - Audit and financial reports 1935 (Box 1)
  - Financial difficulties, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Membership material
  - Applications, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Membership lists (Box 2)
  - Admission Committee (Charles Maley, Chairman) (Box 2)
  - Admission correspondence (Box 2)
- Topical files
  - Anniversary correspondence 1934-1935 (Box 2)
    (includes Albert Einstein letter)
  - Cohen Joseph
    (founder and secretary of the Cooperative)
    - Copies of writings of anarchists for social credo series (Box 2)
    - Letters from individuals discussing their social credos (indexed correspondence) (Box 2)
      (include brief letters from Upton Sinclair and Bolton Hall)
  - Dissolution of Cooperative (Box 2)
  - Factionalism and administrative reorganization, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Land and property
    - Warranty deeds, mortgages (Box 2)
    - Property (non real estate) acquisition (Box 2)
  - Sunrise Schools miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Virginia Sunrise Cooperative
    - Establishment (Box 2)
    - Minutes and financial statement (Box 2)
    - Dissolution (Box 2)
  - Wolverine Cooperative Exchange (Box 2)
- Litigation
  - Court case: Sanders vs. Sunrise Cooperative (Box 2)
  - Sanders vs. Sunrise Coop. August 1936
    (microfilm no. BJ)
    - Proceedings (Reel 1)
    - Proceedings (Reel 2)
    - Newsletters (Reel 2)
    - Decision in Sanders case (Reel 2)